Most deployment failures happen because of a human error or a
configuration drift between the environments.
I'm going to show you how to eliminate those risks by implementing a fully
automated continuous delivery pipeline using Google Cloud Deploy,
Skaffold, and Kustomize.
Let's go to our cloud console. Now here what I have done
is I have created the two clusters.
If I go down to our Kubernetes engine and if I show you the clusters there,
here we have two clusters.
One is dev‑cluster.
Another one is a prod‑cluster.
Also, I have created a sample Flask app.
Let me show you that.
I have created a folder, my‑app‑repo.
Inside that folder, I have my main.py.
In the main.py, you can see that we have a sample
application of Flask that is just saying hello.
Now we want this Flask application to behave differently in
dev than what it does in the production.
Now rather than me doing a manual tweak,
we're going to let our pipeline handle the environment logic,
the container scaling, and the deployment safely all through the code.
The brain of this setup is the customize. Look at our base folder.
Now inside this base folder,
it has a generic blueprint like deployment.yaml file that tells you
what is the name of the app and other information,
and we have the kustomization.yaml that contains the
deployment.yaml and service.yaml information.
Important thing here is the overlays.
Under this overlays folder, I have created two folders.
One is for the dev environment and another one is
for the production environment.
And inside the dev, we have the kustomization.yaml that is
specific for the development environment.
We are telling Kubernetes to keep it simple here
into our development environment.
However, in the production environment, I'm specifically saying that Kubernetes,
please have the two replicas because I'm setting here the count as 2.
So when it deploys in the development environment, it creates one replica.
When it deploys in the production, it will create the two replicas.
And here in the clouddeploy.yaml file, you can see
that we have created a pipeline,
and that pipeline is saying that it has two stages.
At line number 7 and at line number 9,
you can see that we will have one development stage and one is
the production stage. And at line number 17,
I'm giving the cluster information about the dev cluster, and at line
number 24, I'm giving the cluster information about the production
cluster. And if I show you this skaffold.yaml,
now skaffold.yaml contains all the information about the path for the
development environment and for the production environment.
You can look at the line number 14.
It is showing the development environment‑related
information and line number 18 is showing where it can find
the production‑related information.
Now we're going to use this skaffold to build our
container image, and later on we're going to use Cloud
Deploy to deploy that specific build.
So let's just open the terminal. Now I'm scaffold
build command to build the artifacts.
Let me first get into my folder, that is my‑app‑repo.
Inside my folder, I'm going to run the skaffold
build command saying skaffold build.
Now it is going to build an image for us. So you can see that our build has
been successfully created and image has been pushed as well.
Now it's time to go ahead and create the pipeline.
So for pipeline creation,
I'm going to run this simple command saying gcloud deploy,
and I already have delivery‑pipeline.yaml that contains all the
information like we should have two stages.
One is development and the second one is production.
So let me hit the Enter,
and this is going to create a pipeline which will have two stages.
Now it seems like the pipeline has been created.
Let's just go to the Cloud Deploy and see if we have the pipeline ready.
So I go down to the Cloud Deploy, and there you can
see that we got a flask‑pipeline.
If I click on this flask‑pipeline, you can see we have two stages.
One is for dev, and another one is the prod.
So our pipeline got created successfully.
Now it's time to go ahead and create the release.
Once you create the release, it will deploy to the dev environment,
and from there on we're going to promote it to the production environment.
So let's go back to the console,
and this time I'm going to write a command to create the release.
So I'm running a command gcloud deploy release.
This is going to create the release,
and I'm going to give the name as release‑0001 and delivery‑pipeline,
and I'm giving my region as well.
Let's hit Enter.
Now you can see that it has created the release.
Now if we go back to our Cloud Deploy,
go to the delivery pipelines, now here you can see that
release‑0001 is there. You can click on that release, and you
can see that it is in the progress.
It will take a while and once everything goes right,
you will see a green mark here saying that it has deployed
successfully into the dev environment.
Meanwhile, it is in progress.
If you want to see the logs, you can click on that,
and here you can keep on seeing all the logs on the right‑hand side column.
Now great, you can see that it has deployed successfully,
and we are seeing the green mark. Now, let me go back
to the release. And in this release, if on these three dots,
if I click,
I can see the View rollouts, which give me all the information it has
used in the manifest file and the scaffold.yaml.
Now you can go to the pipeline, and here you can see that
we have the deployment done up to dev completely. And if
this looks perfectly fine,
you can click on the Promote, and under the Promote, you can check here
Manifest difference. And you can see that it is saying that when it is
going to do the deployment at line number 33,
the replicas it is going to create is two because we have
written in our production overlays file saying that in the
production we want are two copies of it.
Now you can say that promote, and now the deployment for the
production gets started. And if everything goes fine,
this will get successfully deployed into the production environment as well.
Done.
So you can see that we have successfully pushed our
code into the production as well.
That's how you can move your code from dev to the prod
without doing any manual intervention.